"The Single Most Important Thing for Anti-Aging Skin Care"
Considered the single most
important practice
for maintaining youthful skin:
the daily application
of sunscreen
and taking
other protective measures,
like wearing a hat.
All the other things
you can do for your skin
pale in comparison,
especially for those
with pale skin.
Up to 90 percent
of visible facial aging
among people
with lighter skin tones
is due to exposure to sunlight.
Those with darker skin
are relatively protected
due to their built-in
melanin sunscreen,
but they're still affected.
Sun damage in darker skin
tends to be less about wrinkles
and more
about pigmentation issues,
such as uneven skin tone,
dark patches,
and small dark bumps
on the face.
Either way,
dermatologists now agree
that there is
nothing more important
to slow the signs of aging
than to protect your skin
from the sun.
To illustrate, here's
a dramatic photo of a trucker
who spent decades
getting more sun
on the left side of his face
through
his driver's side window,
reminiscent of a Batman villain.
Factors like sun exposure
and smoking
can make us look
up to 11 years older.
Compare that to extensive
cosmetic surgery—
a face lift and a neck lift,
and removing excess skin
from both the upper
and lower eyelids,
and a forehead lift,
which combined,
can make us look
about eight years younger.
So, a healthy lifestyle
may work even better.
Protecting your skin
from the sun
should be a lifelong endeavor.
This can involve
applying sunscreen,
wearing sun-protective clothing,
hats, and sunglasses,
and avoiding direct sunlight
during the peak hours
of 10:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m.
and instead
seeking shady, covered areas.
Sunbathing is frowned upon,
even with sunscreens
like zinc oxide
or titanium dioxide that offer
broad-spectrum protection
against both UVA
and UVB rays.
We now know
that other wavelengths,
such as near infrared,
that are not covered
by sunscreens
also contribute to skin aging.
Men and women
who use tanning beds
appear significantly older
than those who don't,
and white women who sunbathe
appear years older
than they actually are,
similar to what is seen
with smoking.
UVA rays are primarily
responsible for skin aging,
whereas UVB are the rays
that cause sunburn,
but a broad-spectrum sunscreen
covering both is recommended
since both types of UV
contribute to cancer risk.
To prevent skin cancer,
the American Academy
of Dermatology recommends
sunscreen with an SPF of 30
or higher,
but an SPF even as low as 15
can help prevent skin aging.
How do we know?
Because it's been
put to the test.
Despite the widespread belief
that the use of sunscreen
would prevent skin aging,
all we had was data
on hairless mice.
That is, until ten years ago.
Nine hundred adults
were randomized
either to years
of daily sunscreen use
or to continue with
their own discretionary use.
(It was considered unethical
to withhold protection
by giving people
placebo sunscreen.)
In the end, 77 percent
in the recommended
daily sunscreen group
were applying sunscreen
at least three to four days
per week
compared with only 33 percent
in the discretionary use group.
Would that be
enough of a difference
to make a difference?
Yes, there was
significantly less skin aging
in the instructed
daily use group.
In fact, they suffered
no detectable increase
in skin aging
over the four-and-a-half-year
study.
The researchers concluded
"Regular sunscreen use
retards skin aging in healthy,
middle-aged men and women."